Hello everyone, can you hear me?
Good.
Again, I'm going to have to decline
request to record this using Otter
because
when Otter records the audio, Zoom's own
recording often fails.
We'll wait for a few seconds and we'll
begin.
All right.
So, let's begin.
We're going to continue our series of
lectures on sequence-to-sequence models.
The uh
problem of sequence-to-sequence modeling
is simple.
Instead of
computing scalar or vector inputs from
scalar or outputs from scalar or vector
inputs,
we now compute sequence outputs
from sequence inputs. So, now a sequence
of data instances, a time series, or any
other kind of sequence goes into the
model,
and a sequence comes out. We saw there
are different variants of this problem.
The particular variant we're looking at
today and in the last class was one
uh there's no obvious correspondence
between what goes into the system and
what comes out. For example, what goes
in could be I ate an apple. This is a
machine translation system which come
What comes out is Ich habe einen Apfel
gegessen. And if you hear closely at
this,
you won't see an obvious one-to-one
correspondence between the input and
output.
It can be
uh much
much worse than this if you were a
dialogue system.
If the input was my screen is blank, and
the output is please check if your
computer is plugged in,
there's no visible correspondence at all
between the output and the input. This
is the kind of model we're looking at.
And we saw
that the kind of model we need for that
is the delayed sequence-to-sequence
model
where you have an input component
which processes the entire input to
generate a hidden representation,
and then the output component which
starts off from this initial hidden
representation,
and recurrently generates the output.
But then this naive implementation had
an issue that the output at any time
uh
does not influence outputs at future
times because each word that is output
depends only on the hidden state and not
on the previous outputs.
And so we solved this problem by having
the output be fed back
into the input at each time. So this was
the delayed self-referencing
sequence-to-sequence model.
And so the overall process for this
was that the input sequence,
which we assume is terminated with an
end-of-sequence marker, is first
processed by the
uh initial portion of the network,
the network that processes the input,
and this generates a hidden
representation
at the end-of-sequence marker,
and then subsequently the second network
uses this hidden activation as an
initial state
and a start of sequence marker as an
initial symbol to produce a sequence of
outputs.
So, the output at each time also,
because of because of this
uh
uh self-recurrent output at each time
also becomes
uh the input at the next time. And
output continues until an end of
sequence marker is produced. So, this
hidden state will be fed in along with
the start of sequence marker, you
produce the next word,
which is fed in along with the previous
hidden state,
and you continue this process till an
end of sequence marker is generated. And
so, the output sequence here is what is
produced by the system
in response to the input sequence over
here.
The portion of the network that
processes the input
was what we call the encoder.
And the portion of the network that uses
the final hidden representation from the
input from the encoder
to generate the output sequence was what
we called
the decoder.
Now, we also mentioned that that the
decoder is not performs a specific it's
it's a very specific kind of model. What
did we say the decoder was when it in
terms of language? What did we say the
decoder was? Anybody remember?
What was the decoder?
Anyone?
What did we say it was?
It was a language model. What kind of
language model?
Anyone?
A translator? No.
What kind of language model was the
decoder?
Next token prediction.
It was
It was a conditional language model. Do
you remember that?
It's not just a plain old language
model, it's a conditional language
model. And what is it conditioned
conditioned on?
What was it conditioned on?
The output.
The
It's conditioned on the input, right?
So,
the decoder is a conditional language
model, which models the language
conditioned on whatever is in the input.
Now, this is a much more complex problem
than simple language modeling because in
language modeling you're treating the
language model entire language as a
whole.
In the In conditional language modeling,
you need to know exactly how to model
the language in response to every
possible input. So, as a
in principle, this is a humongously
exponentially more complex problem than
straightforward language modeling. And
that's the task that these models are
performing.
Is everybody with me so far?
Did all of that
ring a bell? That makes sense?
All right. And also, do you see why this
is more complex than just straight-up
language modeling?
Can somebody tell me why it's more
complex than straight-up language
modeling?
Anyone?
Anybody?
So, it's Okay, in language modeling,
you're computing the probability
distribution of all possible sentences
in the language. That's what a language
model does.
It computes the probability that if you
randomly generated some a sentence from
the language,
uh it would be a particular sentence. It
computes probabilities for every
possible sentence in the language.
There's one such distribution.
In the conditional language modeling,
you're computing the probability
distribution over all possible sentences
in the language
conditioned on the input. Now, this
means that there are Just give me a
second. There's a lot of noise outside.
>> So,
this means
that there are as many language models
as there are possible inputs.
Is that making sense?
Depending on the input, the probability
distribution of our sentences changes,
does it not?
If
the person says, "I ate an apple." then
"Ich habe einen Apfel gegessen." is
going to be far more uh
you know, probable than "Guten Morgen."
right?
So,
this means that you're actually modeling
an infinity of language models, one for
every possible input. And all of that is
being done by a single model.
This is way more complicated than
straight-up language modeling.
Is everybody with me
on that so far?
Yes.
Give me some thumbs up if that makes
sense. Give me thumbs up if that makes
sense.
I have like three of them. Today I'm
going to expect at least 15 thumbs up,
right?
Yes. This means that there is a language
model for every possible input, and
somehow we must encapsulate it all in a
single model, V-model.
And that's the task we're dealing with,
which is why it's so complex.
Okay, wait.
Is that a question for me? No, no, like
we think like 30 seconds. So, Guys, can
you please mute yourself?
Right, okay.
So, now there's a problem with this
framework. The framework problem is
Guys, can you mute yourself?
Wait, how do I mute everybody?
Okay, yes, can you mute everybody,
please? Okay.
So,
someone is unmuted.
Please.
If you're in class, mute yourself. Okay.
Now, there's a problem with this
framework, and the problem is this.
The entire input is being represented by
this one hidden state
that the encoder computes at at the end
of sequence marker.
Now, this gets overloaded. This gets
overloaded in two ways. First, on the
decoder side,
this is passed down recurrently through
the entire decoding process. This is a
recurrent network. As you go down
through time, as we saw earlier when we
were discussing the memory capabilities
of recurrent networks, this information
gets diluted because
even in the best case, it gets it keeps
getting overlaid with additional
information that comes from subsequent
inputs. So, by the time you get to the
end of the sentence, say "Gegessen."
This information is going to be almost
completely absent.
Because what you have over here is
entirely is is dominated by the previous
outputs.
Particularly the output is long,
the trailing end of the output is going
to be almost entirely based only on the
past outputs and will have very little
dependence on what happened in the
input.
Does that make sense?
That this is diluting things, right?
I see a single yes. What about the rest
of you guys? Does that make any sense to
the rest of you?
Okay.
Do you see a second problem over here on
the input side?
Can you see a second problem on the
input side?
Anyone?
So,
it relies too much on the final hidden
state, right?
The thing is this, by the time this guy,
the information in the first word
travels all the way over here,
this is going to be so faint
that
that it's not going to provide enough
signal signal to the decoding.
As the input gets longer and longer,
uh the uh
uh input, the the information from the
early portions of the input,
gets very diluted.
Now, we can try to address
the second problem, which is that this
information gets diluted as you go
through the network,
by simply feeding this directly to the
hidden state at every time.
Does the solution making sense?
This is only the solution to the second
problem.
Right?
But, it still doesn't solve
the first problem. Now, when I do this,
now the input encoder has become
separated from the decoder because it's
not just going to the first
uh hidden state. It's not the decoder
has its own recurrence with its own
initial hidden state, and this guy gets
fed everywhere.
But, then the second problem is this,
that all the information about the input
sequence is embedded into a single
vector,
the hidden node layer at the end of the
input sequence, and this is overloaded
with information if the input is long.
Now, if you look carefully, right? This
I
is going to get almost the contribution
of this I is going to get vanishingly
small by the time you get here.
But, then if you uh
uh actually think about what happens,
every single one of these guys carries
information
uh to the decoder.
And specific and more importantly,
specific portions of the output
are more dependent on specific portions
of the input. So, if this I gets
completely diluted by the time it gets
here, and if this is the only thing that
gets with that goes into the first step
of the decoder, the decoder may not
actually be able to distinguish that it
has to translate an I into an ish,
because the whole thing has been has
been diluted. The ish relates directly
to this I. This haben gegen
relate directly to the eight. So, every
output is directly related to some
relevant portion of the input, and the
portion of the input that each output is
related to is going to differ from
output symbol to output symbol.
And this model
is relate is losing this direct
relationship. So, how could you solve
this? How could you make sure that this
guy doesn't get diluted by the time it
get comes here?
And goes into the decoder. Any ideas?
Any suggestions for how you could fix
that?
Feed everything. Right, perfect. So, you
can't feed everything, because the input
is an arbitrary is arbitrarily long,
but then you could average them all, and
that way you make sure that each of them
has equal contribution to this final
value, which is fed at every stage of
the decoder.
And so, this kind of resolves both
problems.
Right? Yes or no?
What do you think?
How many of you think this solves the
problem completely, or there's still
something left to be
addressed?
Okay. There's always something left. So,
Edward, what could be left?
Well, I when I give you a leading
question, that's always the answer,
right? Position. So, what is left?
We might not. That's right. Is averaging
a good idea? I'm giving
as much importance to I as I'm giving to
Apple
when I'm averaging everything, but Ish
doesn't care very much for Apple. Ish is
interested in I.
On the other other hand, off field cares
for Apple.
Off field is not interested in I, right?
So, what we really want is so, the
problem
problem is that the average applies the
same weight to every input. It applies
the same average to every output word.
In practice, different outputs may be
related to different inputs, right? So,
what we would like is a different
weighted combination of of the inputs
feeding to each guy. Now, again, we
don't know how to weight them.
We don't In this example, it may be
obvious, but typically when this guy is
being generated, we don't know which of
the inputs is important to it.
But somehow, we would like to have an
importance weighted average, which is
different at each time.
This is what we will call a context
vector.
A context vector is a weighted average
of these inputs where the weights depend
on the specific output being generated.
Is this making sense?
Yes or no?
Right?
So, what would be required of these
weights
for this to work?
What would be required of these weights?
Anyone?
What would be required? Updates?
Well, this would work. So, here's what
we'd have, right?
This guy is going to have some set of
weights. This is the zeroth output, so I
have put the zero over here. I is the
index of the input. You get a weighted
sum of inputs. This guy is going to use
one set of weights.
This guy is going to use a completely
different set of weights as indicated by
the parenthesis one, which means it's
the first output is that's being
generated. The subscript I refers to the
input index.
This third guy is using a a third set of
weights.
The fourth set guy is still using a
fourth set of weights. The fifth guy is
setting using a fifth set of weights and
so on, right?
So,
uh every single output is combining
these hidden states using a different
set of weights. And this would work if
the weights could be somehow made to
focus on the right input word.
Somehow magically, when we are trying to
generate apple, we should be able to
compute weights that give greater
importance to apple and very little to
I. On the other hand, when I'm
generating onion,
the word the weights must somehow
focus on an and ignore the apple, right?
We need
a a mechanism for computing weights
that knows somehow what to focus on when
the things are combined.
That making sense?
Yes or no?
Right.
So, that's what we need, right?
How do we do that?
The weights must be dynamically
computed.
And the weights must be computed
dynamically as some function of the
decoder state because when I'm
generating apple,
the decoder this is the decoder is in a
specific state and that state should
inform
what to focus on, right? And the
expectation is that if the model is well
trained, this will automatically
highlight the correct input.
But then we go back to Abhinav's
question, how do we compute these?
For this, let's go back and look at what
we have at our disposal
when
we are trying to generate output, right?
When I'm trying to trying to generate
output, the only information the decoder
has is the hidden state in the previous
at the previous word, right?
This is what we have. This is the
complete This is the summary of
everything that's happened so far. Do
you or do you not agree
at this point?
Right? Yes. So, somehow we need to be
able to use this guy and each of these
H's to decide what the weight must be
for each of these inputs. So, the weight
corresponding to each input has got to
be some function
of the hidden state for the input and
the decoder state at the previous
output. That makes sense?
This weight has to be a function of HI,
the weight of the Ith input at the Tth
output must be a function of the hidden
state HI at the Ith input and the state
ST - 1 the decoder state at the previous
output.
That clear to everybody?
Yes or no?
Right. Okay, so give me a few thumbs up
if that makes sense.
Okay.
But then I have another requirement.
And what is that requirement? Let's say
in the vector space, these H's are all
out here. So, these are my 1 2 3 4 5
H's, right?
The weighted average of these guys would
it be okay for this weighted average to
be anywhere at all? Like out here or
here or here? Would that make sense? Or
would you want those to be somewhere in
this hull?
Where would you want the weighted sum?
Uh that's right, everyone. So, where
would you the weighted the average to
be? Inside this hull or anywhere at all?
What makes more sense?
In the middle, right? How do you ensure
that it's in the on the
inside? How would you ensure that it's
on the inside?
Anyone?
How would you ensure that it's on the
inside?
The red points are the ages, these five
ages in my example.
Softmax.
So, here's a property of polytopes,
right?
Any point on the inside of the polytope
is going to be
a weighted sum of the
vertices
where the weights sum to one.
So, if the weights are all positive and
sum to one, then any weighted sum is
going to be inside this polytope.
If any of the weights become positive or
negative or if the weights don't sum to
one, then the weighted sum can go
outside.
That makes sense?
Yes or no?
That makes sense to everybody.
I'd like to see some thumbs ups.
Okay, and so we want these weights to
offer at any given output time. The
weights assigned to all the inputs must
be positive and they must sum to one.
On the other hand, if I just have an
arbitrary function of this kind,
so
for Nars, what do you mean by explain
the W? The W's are the weights with
which these guys are combined, right?
The The W's are the weights with which
these hidden states
What does the sum to one indicate? The
sum to one basically says that if these
are my original hidden states,
and if I take a weighted sum, then the
weighted sum is going to be inside
the polytope
that and that envelopes the
hidden states. That answers the
question. Yes.
So, okay.
Now,
this guy, does this guarantee that the
weights are positive, let alone sum to
one?
Yes or no?
Does it?
No. So, how do you make it sum to one?
And how do you make them all positive?
Any suggestions?
How would I make them normalize?
Normalize will only make them sum to
one, but it won't guarantee that they're
positive, right?
Absolute softmax. So, there are
different techniques of doing this. You
can take the absolute and take a
normalize or whatever, but what we will
do is to have a two-step process. First,
we compute some arbitrary function of
the hidden state and the ST minus one.
And then you put the collection of these
EIs one corresponding to each of these
guys through a softmax, and that
guarantees that the weights are now
positive and they sum to one. And those
weights are what I use to average these
hidden values to compute the
the computer context vector at any time.
And so, that leads us to our very first
point.
>> Okay, 5 seconds, guys.
All right, let me end this poll.
And can anybody give me the answers?
What are the answers?
True, false, true, right?
So, that engine framework computes a
different context vector at each output
step. The context vector is not chosen
to be the input with the highest
attention weight.
The attention weight is a function of
the hidden encoder representation and
the most recent decoder state. Somehow
over here I slipped
in the word attention because these
weights are basically these are what we
call attention weights. They decide
which portion of the input the model
pays attention to in generating any
output. Any input that has a high weight
is being paid a lot of attention.
So, we saw that the attention weights
must be computed using a two-step
process. The first is compute some some
arbitrary
function of the hidden state and
of the encoder state and the
decoder state at the previous time.
And that's put through a softmax. But
what is this function G?
Many different Gs have been proposed in
the literature.
If the encoder hidden states and the
decoder states have the same
dimensionality,
then this G can simply be an inner
product between the two.
But if the encoder state is say
uh
10 components long and the decoder state
is say 20 components long,
how can I combine these two in a linear
manner
to get a scalar?
How would I combine these two if both of
them are the same length?
Then it's easy. I just take A transpose
B. This is going to give me a scalar,
right?
But if they are different lengths, how
can I compute a scalar from this?
Anyone?
What what can I do? Pad?
If I pad, I'm going to lose stuff,
correct?
If I pad, that means I'm going to be
ignoring everything. There's a So, here
is what we will do.
I'm going to take this short guy, I'm
going to take this long guy, and then in
between, I'm going to put in a matrix
which makes the sizes match up.
So, this if this is less size N and this
is if this is size M, this is going to
be an N cross M matrix, and this matrix
will be learned. That's my WG. And now
the product is a scalar. Does that make
sense to everybody?
Yes, no?
Right.
And so, this is what we're going to do.
Can I see a few thumbs ups?
That we are we're good so far.
I see.
Okay. And so, there are other functions
that have been proposed in the
literature like the stand HRN and MLP,
but they're not very popular.
And the simple HWS, where W is learned,
is what is most common. So, let's take a
look at a typical conversion process
assuming this as an example. Here's what
would happen.
The input is going to pass through the
encoder to produce this hidden states at
every time.
Then the decoder is a recurrent model,
it has an initial state which can be set
to some fixed value like a vector of
ones or a vector of zeros, or maybe the
average of all of these H's multiplied
by a matrix. Uh there are different ways
of setting this up.
Subsequently, at the very first time,
we're going to use S of minus one with
all of these H's to compute the raw
attention weight, which is just the
matrix inner product between the H and
the S.
And then these raw attention weights are
going to be
put through a softmax to compute the
attention weights for the zeroth output.
And these hidden states are going to be
combined with these attention weights to
give you the context vector for the
zeroth output.
So, the decoder takes in a start of
sequence marker, this context vector,
and the initial
hidden state. The initial hidden state
was also used to compute these attention
weights, and then the decoder generates
an output probability distribution over
all the words
from which a word is drawn.
And then that's at the next time this
word is fed back in. But now this is the
most recent decoder hidden state. So,
this decoder hidden state is now used
with all of all of these H's
to generate the raw attention weight,
which is then convert to it converted to
a probability distribution using a soft
max.
And then you compute this context
vector.
This is the These are the attention
weights.
And then you compute the context vector
as a weighted sum of all of the hidden
values.
That context vector and the first word
and the previous hidden state are now
fed into the recurrent hidden layers
over here,
which then compute the next probable the
probability distribution for the next
word,
from which the next word is drawn.
And now
you just continue the process. Now you
have the hidden state S1, which is used
to compute the attention weights for
all the inputs. Those weights are used
to compute the next context vector.
The next context vector, the previous
word harbor, and the previous recurrent
hidden state are all fed into the
current
hidden state computation to generate the
next output
the probability distribution for the
next word,
from which the next word is drawn, and
so on, and you continue this process
until you draw an end of sequence
marker.
Did this process make sense to
everybody?
This decoding process, yes or no?
So,
which word would Okay.
So, this is the attention-based
decoding.
At each time, you compute a raw hidden
state,
a raw raw attention weight from the
hidden state of the previous time,
and the encoder hidden state, you put it
through a soft max
to compute the attention weights. Then
you compute at the weighted sum of these
hidden state values to compute the
context,
and then the context, the previous
hidden state, and the previous word
output are all used to compute the
probability distribution for the next
word
from which the word is drawn.
So, to answer Sriram's question, we'll
get to that in a bit.
But then,
we're going to make We're going to
introduce a few minor modifications,
right?
So, let's say I'm
uh I'm I'm drawing I'm generating the
word apple, right?
Uh
So, see you. This is the raw attention
weight.
E I T is in my case, for example, this
guy, right?
So, E I is this one here.
Which is basically H W S.
Is there any guarantee that this is
positive, Sriram?
Is there any guarantee that it's
positive?
So, how do I convert it to something
that's positive where the E I's for all
of these guys sum to one?
I put it through a soft max. So, it's a
two-step process. First, I compute the
raw attention weight.
That's the E I.
And then the raw attention weight is put
through a soft max to compute the actual
attention weight.
Right?
That's why you need the intermediate E
I's.
Okay.
So,
now going back to my question here.
When I'm generating the word apple,
clearly, I must focus on this guy,
right?
But is it the fact that it's an apple
specifically that makes it important, or
is it the fact that it's just a fruit
that can be eat eaten? Because I said
eat.
What is important? Should I be actually,
when I decide this, compute this
attention weight?
Is the fact of it being the an apple,
specifically, key, or is it just
relevant that it's a fruit?
What is the important bit?
The fact that it's a fruit, right? Being
something to eat. On the other hand,
when I generate the context,
in the context, should I be just
considering the fact that it's a fruit,
or should I consider the fact that
there's that it's an apple,
specifically?
What should I be doing?
The fact that it's an apple. So, there
are two different things that are going
on. When I'm computing the attention
weight, it's sufficient for me to
realize that it's a fruit.
But, when I compute the context, I
should consider that it's actually an
apple, right? Yes or no?
That makes sense, right?
And so,
if that made sense, then give me a
thumbs up.
I'm going to take it from there.
So,
did that did that make sense for us,
guys? Okay, it did, right? So, how do we
deal with this dichotomy? The way we
will deal with this dichotomy is
actually generate two different values
from the hidden state over here.
So, Edward,
when I'm trying to
generate a context for apple,
I'm computing attention weights for all
of these guys, right?
Is the attention weight that I give to
apple specific,
depends specifically on it being an
apple,
or should I take into consideration that
it's something that's that can be eaten?
For the weight itself,
when I decide what to pay attention
import what is important
is the apple that important or the is
the mere fact that it's something to be
eaten?
What's important everyone?
Just that it said something to eat,
right? On the other hand, the context
that I generate from it must
specifically capture apple because
that's what I'll be translating, right?
So, I have two different things going on
at the same time.
And so, the way we will deal with it is
we're going to generate
two terms from this age. One is what
we'll call a key, which captures crude
higher-level information. This is going
to capture information that it's
something to eat.
And then we're going to capture
something called a value,
which is
which captures specifically the fact
that it's an apple, okay? And so,
this
the way we will generate these two
values is through two matrices, one of
which will project it down to the key
space, the other projects it into the
value space. And then you have a query.
The query may be a different dimension
from these guys, so the query is going
to have its own
weight matrix to move it down to the
same dimension.
And so,
what we will do now is to use this query
with this key to generate attention
weights.
And when you use the query with this
with this key,
the key is sort of extracting crude
information
that this is a
fruit. And so, you're going to use the
query with the key to generate attention
weights, but then once you got the
attention weights, you're going to
actually combine the you're going to get
a weighted sum of the values.
And the values capture the fact that
it's an apple. That makes sense to
everybody?
The weight depends on the key and the
query.
And the context depends on the
weights and the value.
And the key says this is a fruit, the
value says
this is a And the the query came from
the the previous hidden state.
I just projected it down into the same
dimension as K.
And the K and the V came V came from
this hidden state.
That That clear, Vimana?
Right.
Did this make sense to everybody?
What we just did?
Right?
Yes, okay.
And a special case I'm just going to say
K equals V equals H, Q equals S minus 1,
and that's sort of being somewhat crude,
but we do that all the time. I mean, I'm
going to use that for my explanations.
And the other thing that Sriram asked,
"How do I generate outputs, right?" As
before, the objective of drawing is to
produce the most likely output
that generates an end-of-sequence
marker.
Which means I want to generate the
sequence of outputs
such that the product of the
probabilities
assigned to each of these outputs is
maximum, keeping in fact that the
outputs keep getting fed back to the
input. Have we seen this
statement before?
Have we seen this before?
Yes or no?
Where have we seen this?
Guys,
where did we see this?
Anybody, come on.
Alignment?
Divergence in Did you see this in the
last class by any chance?
We saw this in the last class, didn't
we?
When we say when we were speaking of the
simple translation model,
that we want to produce the output
word sequence that has the highest
probability.
Do you remember that?
We were speaking of greedy, but no, we
were speaking specifically that,
you know, at each time, this model is
going to be generate uh assigning a
probability to every word, right? And
you want to get the word sequence which
has the highest overall probability.
This is the same problem as we had in
the last class.
And you can't so for this you'd have to
compute the probability for every
possible word sequence. This is not
feasible. And so we're going to use a
beam search as before.
At each time
you at time zero feed a start of
sequence marker, get a probability
distribution.
But then you feed each of the inputs and
this hidden state as input at the next
time.
And you're going to get a next
probability distribution. You're going
to keep the top K, right?
Then you're going to expand
uh so now at this time each of these
will have a different context. Not not
in this specific setting, but say if you
went down one time step later each of
these has a previous different previous
hidden state, right? So each of these is
going to get a different context vector
in principle.
And so each of these is going to get
generate a probability distribution.
And you're going to use all the words to
uh as the next possible input, but you
won't use all of them. You're only going
to keep the top K.
And then expand things out and keep
repeating the process
uh so that at no time you're actually
exploring more than 2V options.
And the overall option that you're going
to choose is the one for which
this the product of the sequence of
probabilities is highest. Here I'm using
two as my beam.
In general, you're going to use K as
your beam.
Did this make sense to everybody? I'm
just glossing over it because we spent
some time on this in the last class.
But did this make sense to everybody?
Give me a thumbs up if it made sense.
Maybe I can get times.
If all fantastic.
Right? And then you terminate on the
most likely overall path and and then
end of sequence marker
or continue producing more outputs
to generate the end best outputs.
So so far so good. We've seen how the
inference works. We see how the model
works.
What is the attention look, right?
Do these attention weights actually
capture the relevant information?
The attention weights must capture the
relevant relative importance of each
position in the input
to the current output. And here are some
examples from the original paper on the
subject. Here this was I think
uh this is Bahdanau Bahdanau et al.
They showed an example for translation
from English to French.
So the English sentence is the agreement
on the European Economic Area was signed
in August 1992 period. And this is the
end of sequence marker.
When you translate it, it correctly
translated to
My French pronunciation is awful.
But it comes to l'accord sur
la zone économique européenne a été
signée ah whatever, right?
And so if you look at this, when you're
generating the
the correct when you're generating la
the correct word to to
focus on is the, right?
When you're generating accord,
uh you should be looking at arrangement.
When you're looking at sur, you should
be looking on on. So it's linear. But
then the word order flips
when you go to European Economic Area.
The European Economic Area in English,
the word order is flipped in French it
becomes zone économique européenne. And
so uh this is and note that when it's
trying to generate zone, the attention
weight actually focused on area. When it
was generating économique, it was it
actually generated focused on
économique. European
it generated on European, right? They
focused on European, so in this little
patch, the attention weights actually
sort of reverse their trade to pay
attention on the right thing. So, the
model is actually doing just exactly
what you would expect it to do.
Right?
So,
Edward, what is each key query value?
So, it's over here.
Here, we're going to have some. We're
just using the key query value the query
and key to generate attention weights
and the value to generate context.
That's about it.
Nothing more than that.
Okay. So, there's only one set In the
way I've presented it so far, there's
only one set of key query values.
If you're speaking of multi-head
attention, we haven't yet gotten into
it, okay? But, is Do you guys find this
impressive? It does this again and again
and again. It's beautiful.
It knows what to pay attention to,
right?
And so,
the model really works.
And uh
here are some translation examples. I am
not going to try to pronounce the
French.
Uh but
uh those of you who can read French
can try and there's a whole bunch of us
out here who do know French, they will
will be able to confirm that these
translations are pretty good. These are
this These were the models that they
got.
This was the original Google Translate
they beating, I think.
Uh so, this was by Google, right? So, I
think Google Translate is beating the
all of the others previous models by
uh a pretty big margin, right? And so,
this was a 2016 is where Google
Translate suddenly became a useful tool.
In mid-2016, Google Translate was not
really useful. If you translated English
to French and French back to English,
the input and output would look very
different. And when these attention
models came in, magically, voila,
everything just worked, right?
So,
we have seen how a trained network can
be used to compute outputs, to convert
one sequence to another, but now let's
consider training, right?
In training, I'm going to give an input
and the output is going to be a sequence
of output probability distributions,
against which I compute the reference.
Now, when we discussed this in the last
class, how did we say we train this
model?
Did we train it using the standard
technique that we use for neural
networks, or did we train it as a
language model?
So, Georgina, yes, it worked, right?
Uh you would see you you you it actually
learns. Uh but anyways, how did we say
we train the model in the last class?
Did we train it as a conditional
language model?
We used a different technique of
learning. How did What was different?
What was What was different?
Do you remember?
What was different?
Input output. So, here, we are treating
it as a training a conditional language
model. You're giving it an input, the
target output would be the same as the
input shifted by one. The only extra is
that you're getting this conditioning
input at each time. So, this is
uh and so, this is how you would
actually train the model.
Which means that
you're feeding the input, you're feeding
the output, you're getting the the
target output is the same as the output
shifted,
and during the backward pass, you
compute a divergence between the target
output and output distributions, and you
back propagate everything through the
network.
And the back propagation would also
update any parameters of the attention
function G if you have any, right?
But this is different from your standard
training paradigm.
What it does is that it actually
performs maximum likelihood training of
a conditional language model. You got
this complicated neural network model.
You're giving it the input. You're also
giving it the output as an input because
it's going into the inference. Whereas,
if you were performing actual inference,
you wouldn't have these guys. These guys
would be fully generated. Whereas, here
you're actually giving this guy as
input, right? And then you're comparing
it the output is the same as this guy,
which is shifted.
This is not like regular inference. In
regular inference, what you'd have is
this.
I ate an apple goes in and something
comes out, right? So, do you see the
difference between what's happening here
and what happens here?
Yes or no?
Do you see this
difference?
What about the rest of you guys? I see
two people telling me yes.
If you see the difference, can you
actually give me a thumbs up?
Like 10 of them, so I know at least
1/16 of the class is aligned with me. I
have
Okay, thank you. Right. So,
uh
and why would this not work?
Faranaz, how is it shifted? Look.
Uh I am giving it
I ate an apple over here, ish.
Haber einen Apfel gegessen, but here
it's Haber einen Apfel gegessen end of
sequence. So, when I'm giving it ish,
the desired output is Haber.
So, you see the shift? You're predicting
the next word at each time.
Faranaz, Faranaz.
Right, okay. So,
how why would this not work? Why do you
think I say this won't work? Why would
this not work? Anybody?
Why would this not work?
Any suggestions?
Inference is harder. So, during
training,
this model is going to be crappy in the
beginning. There's no guarantee what
comes out.
Right? How are you going to compare this
guy to a shower and an octal gigasam?
You're not going to be able to do it.
Which is why we train it as
as
a conditional language model. Right?
But from the perspective so this
conditional language model method
ensures a one-to-one correspondence
between the outputs and the desired
output.
But from the perspective of traditional
training it's cheating
uh because during the inference of the
forward pass the ground truth is being
passed in instead of being drawn.
So it's what we are performing what is
called teacher forcing in that the
teacher is being given the is given the
answer.
And the student is being given the
That makes sense?
Yes, no? That makes sense.
Right?
So
there's a why there's a huge gap between
this where you give it only the input
and where you give it the input and the
output.
So this is kind of cheating
and this is probably going to come end
up with a model that's not as well
trained
as if you could train a model using this
approach but this approach is not going
to work. So is there something in
between where you still give it the
truth but not all of it.
So that you can maintain a one-to-one
correspondence between the actual and
desired outputs.
So
this
uh
is what we will call
uh teacher forcing where at each time
at every now and then instead of
giving it the ground truth you're
actually going to draw a sample from
here
and then feed it into the input. So
you're not going to do it at every time.
Uh
what if the the input is always correct,
right? The input is what you give it.
That's this guy. That's your training
data.
So every now and then you're going to
draw something from here and feed it in.
So, it's not fully cheating in some
sense. You're not giving it the entire
answer. You're giving it the partial
answer with some words drawn from the
output, and then you use this to train
your network.
But, this process of drawing from a
distribution is not differentiable.
And so, you end up with a problem that
this process of drawing something from
here and feeding it in here doesn't
allow derivatives to be passed
backwards.
If you don't pass derivatives backwards
over here, it's not going to kill you.
But, it's going to be better if you can.
And for this something you have For this
you have something called the Gumbel
trick, which you'll encounter in the
homework.
And the Gumbel trick says that drawing
from
a category distribution is the same as
adding the log probabilities of the
categories
to a to a a uh
uh Gumbel variable, right? And then
doing it where the Gumbel variable is
drawn from a Gumbel distribution, and
then performing an argmax. This G is
randomly drawn. Log y's are these
probabilities.
And then if you do an argmax, this is
This process is exactly the same as
simply drawing from this distribution.
But, then you can replace an argmax by a
softmax.
And so, the softmax is going to give you
a vector of probabilities which can And
so, that can be uh as the softmax is
differentiable, and so the whole process
becomes differentiable. The process of
sampling. You will see this in your
homeworks, so I won't spend more time on
it.
So, this is the basic attention
framework.
And there have been various extensions,
but like bidirectional processing of the
input sequence.
Uh you have local versus global
attention, other variants. Then, you
also have something called multi-head
attention where, instead of generating
just one key and value from each age,
you can generate multiple keys and
values. And so, the hope is that if you
do this, this guy uses maybe the part of
speech to figure out what it is focusing
on. This guy maybe uses the grammatical
structure to what to to decide what it's
focusing on. So, you get different kinds
of information sources
for uh from the same sequence of hidden
states.
You end up with two context vectors, one
one from this guy and one from this guy,
both of which you'd concatenate
to feed into the decoder. That makes
sense? This is the multi-head attention.
Did this make sense?
Right. Okay. So,
uh so far, so good.
And so, we have our second poll.
And maybe at the end of the second poll,
people can tell me what's up with the
owl eyes
at the end of this lecture.
But, yeah.
15 seconds, guys.
Let me end this poll.
Can you
give me the answers?
What are the answers? Beam,
full tree search, one and two and three.
The optimal decoder is always going to
be the full tree search because the beam
search is actually losing information,
right?
And multi-head attention computes a
separate set of keys and values for each
head at each input.
So it and it So you also need a separate
query
corresponding. So each head has a key
and a value on the query side,
on the input side, and a corresponding
query on the output side.
These models change the world.
Attention-based models are currently
responsible for the state of art in AI.
Everything, right? Everything with a
minor twist.
And we'll get to this shortly. But then
in the you know
just some history,
this is the very first attention-based
captioning model. And you can see the
encoder can be encoding anything. Here
they used the encoded images using a
CNN.
And they used an attention-based
decoder. And you can see how it does a
does a fantastic job. This it captioned
as a woman throwing a Frisbee in a park.
When you look at what it's paid
attention to, when it says produces
Frisbee, it focused on Frisbee. The dog
is standing on a hardwood floor. The
caption's wrong, but when you look at
what it
focused on when it said dog, it got the
dog, right? A stop sign is on a road
with a mountain in the background. It
got the stop sign. This is beautiful. A
giraffe standing in a forest with trees
in the background. If you look at what
it focused on when it said related
trees, it got everything except the
giraffe. It's amazing, right? So this is
the Show, Attend, and Tell uh
Neural Image Caption Generation with
Visual Attention from 2016.
So this is a fantastic model.
Do you guys find this to be impressive?
I do. Especially it's 10 years old.
Right? And things have only gotten
better.
So
we've looked at various forms of
sequence-to-sequence models. We've
looked at generalizations of recurrent
network formalisms, lots of papers.
And we'll appear in homework four,
right? Speech recognition with attention
models.
But then let's go back to the drawing
board.
The input sequence feeds into a
recurrent structure.
And it's terminated by an explicit
end-of-sentence marker.
Our original problem was that if you use
this simple structure, this guy stored
all the information about the sentence,
which the
uh decoder used. This was not okay. So,
to
prevent overloading this guy, we used
uh an uh attention-based frame
mechanism,
where we actually computed
a context vector as a weighted sum of
all of these hidden values.
But then, if I'm computing, explicitly
weighting these guys,
and computing this context, what role
does this recurrence play? Does this
recurrence play any role at all
when the decoder is just automatically
figuring out what to pay attention to?
And how to weight things? Is the
recurrence playing any role? What do you
guys think?
Does it have any role in the process
anymore?
Yes or no?
I see one answer, no. What about the
rest of you guys? What do you think?
All right.
Two.
Are you sort of scared to guess?
Sriram.
Yeah.
No, right?
So, if it's not playing any role, what
can we do with it?
What can we do with it?
How about just get rid of it, right?
And so here we are.
We got rid of attention, boom.
This should still work, right? What do
you think?
They should kind of work, right?
Yes or no?
To give you an indication that it should
work, over here, a CNN was the encoder.
The CNN has no recurrence, yet it did a
great job, right?
So, yeah, yeah, the context vectors
depend on the output. I'm just looking
at what's happening on the input
network.
So, this should work. Do you agree with
me?
Kind of work.
But, we need some fine-tuning.
If this makes sense to you, I will
continue.
Now, there's no But, there's something
that is true, Alex, but there's more
than that. Look at this word apple. Are
we referring to the computer apple? Are
we Or are we referring to the fruit?
What are we referring to when I say
apple?
In this case.
What should I be translating? The fruit.
Where's that information?
Where is the information that it's a
fruit?
It's an eight and it's an apple, right?
So, but mostly in the eight. So, that
means I can't just get an H over here
without actually considering eight.
So, what do I do? This eliminates
context specificity, right? Uh
similarly, uh the embedding for an must
be made depends on the fact that what
follows an apple, right? So, using the
How do we introduce context specificity?
I'm going to use the I'm going to use
the attention framework itself.
The encoder in the sequence-to-sequence
model can be composed without
recurrence, but I'm going to use the
attention framework to introduce context
specificity. This is what we call
self-attention.
So, what do we do?
I'm going to first process all of these
guys to get a first set of hidden
values.
Then, I will have three matrices, one
for the query, one for the key, one for
the value,
and generate a query, key, and value
from each of these cards. Again, the
query and the key and value are
different because the key kind of
captures a different kind of information
in the value.
And the query is different because the
query is what is used to determine what
to pay attention to.
Then, for this first guy, I'm going to
use its query
with the keys for all the words,
including itself,
to generate a set of attention weights.
Then, once it So, you're going to For
that, you're going to use generate raw
attention weights and put them through a
softmax.
Once you do that, I'm going to use these
attention weights
to average the values for all of these
guys,
and that's going to give me an updated
value for H, which is obtained from V.
And in so doing, this O has actually
somehow considered the influence of all
of the neighbors
in the sentence.
I can do that for
So, I'm going to get
for the first output, I'm going to get
attention weights as a function of the
query for that output and all the keys.
And then I get an output as a
combination of the
uh weighted values.
And this is what we call a
self-attention because it's all within
itself, right? This is the
self-attention block, and I can do this
use the same thing for each of these
outputs.
For each guy, I'm going to use its query
with the keys for all of them to
generate attention weights, and then use
those attention weights to combine all
their values to generate the output. Did
this make sense? Did this process make
sense to everybody?
Yes or no?
Give me a thumbs-up if it made sense.
Ask me a question if it did not.
Okay.
So, here we are.
The The Are you good with this, Edward?
Are you Bruno, Edward, are you good with
this?
Okay. So now I'm going to update this
age by using the query for this guy
against the keys for all of these to
generate a bunch of attention weights.
So then I'm going to get a W0, W1. I'm
going to get a bunch of attention
weights.
I'm going to use these attention weights
with these values
and get a weighted sum.
And that weighted sum is going to give
me an updated
version of this age. Did I answer your
question, Edward?
Right. Bruno, I'm going to answer you.
Right. And so I'm going to repeat the
same process for every one of these
guys.
This is what we call self-attention
because you're it's it's all within the
encoder. The sentence is referring to
itself.
Other words to the net.
itself. That's why it's self-attention,
right? And so eventually you're going to
get updates for all of these guys.
How does each of the three influence the
updated age? Again, for Naze.
The query and this query
and this
value
get W0, right? This query and this value
get W1.
So this the query the query for this guy
is going to be used against the key for
all of these guys to get
the various attention weights, right?
Then this weight multiplies this value
and then the whole thing is summed up.
So everything gets involved. Did I
answer your question, Naze?
Yes or no?
Right. And so
that's how you get this whole
self-attention block.
But then, so this is my self-attention
block.
I can use I can generate a query key and
value for each of these edges and get
updated values.
This is what we call a single-head
self-attention block, but then I can do
this many times over where each of them
generates has a different set of
matrices and generates a different set
of queries, keys, and values. The hope
being that each of them captures a
different aspect of the sentence. For
example, one might come capture
semantics, the other might capture
grammatical structure, the third might
capture something else, right? Uh and
so, you're going to get an updated
value O from each of these guys, which
are then all concatenated to get a final
uh updated representation for all of
these edges. And this is what we call
multi-head
attention.
It's multi-head self-attention, but it's
multi-head attention.
That makes sense? What we just did?
Everybody?
Right.
So, that's our multi-head
self-attention. But then this has a
problem
in that if you concatenate them, each of
them is going to be
uh
generating some subsection of the
updated vector,
but you want to mix them up
so that these guys, each of them
influences everything else. How do you
mix them up? You do that very simply.
You stick an MLP on top so that it mixes
everything up.
And this MLP has a very large number of
parameters. It turns out that this MLP
is where all the information that the
model learns is stored.
And that's going to give you the final
representation, which has been derived
from these edges.
That makes sense to everybody?
Why do you want to mix them? Because if
I don't mix them, then each of them
keeps working locally. And so, what you
learn over here never never informs what
happens here.
That answer your question, Anna?
Right. You want each You want the part
of speech to inform structure. You want
the structure to inform part of speech,
things like that. So, you want to mix
them up.
Did that answer you?
I'm assuming so, right?
What does YI represent? So, I is the
index, H0, Y0, H1, Y1, and so on.
H2 became Y2.
Did that answer you? I assume so, right?
So, from H0, I got these O0s.
O
So, from the Hs, I got the Os using
multi-head self-attention and MLP mixed
it up to get the Ys.
And so, this whole thing is the
multi-head self-attention block.
Right.
YI has the
uh it's not just that Yeah. YI has the
updated representation of H where it has
considered not just itself, but also the
influence of the others other terms in
the sentence.
Did that answer you, Edward?
Right. And uh
So, Sean, no. This this MLP, it's not
it's not a sequence MLP. I'm just
drawing this as an MLP, but there's a
there's a single MLP operating on each
guy
to generate the Ys.
So, the figure is perhaps wrong.
Right?
And there's no non- The non-linearity
is, you know, you're you're you're
computing this uh weighted sum. There's
a softmax. The softmax is a
non-linearity. So,
I should probably update my figure to
reflect what Sean just pointed out. I've
been careless, right? But this is a
multi-head self-attention block.
And the encoder can include many such
layers of
self-attention. But then there's one
thing more that you want to consider.
So, look at this word eight.
The word eight influences apple if it's
just preceding this. But if I had like a
300-word sentence and the word eight
occurred somewhere out here, should this
eight influence the represent of
representation of apple?
You could say, you know, I ate an orange
and afterwards I worked on my apple
computer, right?
And in that case the eight should it
still influence the apple the same way
as this eight?
Or should it have lower weight?
Right. So,
the distance of the words matters,
right?
How far away it is from the current word
should matter.
And this framework doesn't consider the
distance because you're just looking at
the keys and the queries,
but uh the key but the queries and the
keys, but there's nothing about
position.
So, we capture position
through something called a position
embedding.
The attention that a vector VT pays to
an attention a vector at VT plus tau
here doesn't depend on T plus capital T
doesn't depend on T.
So, if the same word eight occurred 20
times, the attention that apple would
pay to every instance of eight would be
the same and this is not right.
So, the way we deal with it is to add
some kind of structured noise to these
H's
such that when you compute the inner
product between the query and the key,
as you go away, this inner product
falls off. And so, the the the weight
that you get tapers off.
That makes sense? I'm not just going to
use H. It's going to be some H plus some
some term. H plus some term. And the
term that I add is such that when I look
at the inner product of H3 and H1, if I
had the same eight out here, that extra
term added over here is going to be of
the same kind as that this inner product
will be much lower than this inner
product. Did that make sense?
Yes or no, right?
And so
this is what we're going to do. We're
going to be working with these word
embeddings.
And we will add something called a
positional encoding to capture the
relative distance of things to
uh
one another.
And the positional encoding has one
characteristic
that the positional encoding vector
length is going to be the same for all
of them because you don't want to add
uh
impose some uh
unnecessary importance by giving
different lengths.
And secondly, the the product of the
positional embeddings between the the
relationship between two positional
embeddings
should be such that P of T plus tau
is some M of tau times P of T where M of
tau depends only on the distance between
the two. So, that means that if the
whole sentence is shifted by a bit,
the the influence of the positional
embedding doesn't change. It only
depends on the gap between the two words
being considered.
And so
uh did this make sense? And look
Did this make sense?
Right? And so
a standard positional embedding vector
is something that's composed of a whole
bunch of sines and cosines
and where of different frequencies.
And the sines and cosines of different
frequencies have this property that M
that M of tau has a
uh this P of T and P of T plus tau
is related through a matrix which is
given by this formula. I'm not going to
get into it in some detail And in any
detail. I wanted to convey the concept.
You will be working with positional
embeddings in
uh
your homework.
And so the relate the the linear
relationship between TT and PT of tau
enables the net to learn shift invariant
gap dependent relationships.
Did this make sense?
Yes, no?
Okay.
And so this is the self-attending
encoder.
That's on the encoder.
Can we use the same mechanism on the to
replace the recurrence in the decoder? I
mean
I don't need recurrence in the encoder.
Why do I need it in the decoder? It
turns out I don't, right? I can use the
same self-attention mechanism in the
decoder
but with one difference.
In the encoder, when I'm trying to get
the updated representation for H2
I can also use these guys. So when I'm
getting an updated representation for
eight I can also use the use apple
in generating the updated representation
for eight.
In the decoder, the words are being
generated one at a time. So when I
generate eight
I don't have access to apple. Apple has
not yet been generated. So at each time,
things in the future are absent. So on
the encoder
it to generate the updated
representation for any guy, I can use
everything including words in the past
and words in the future, right?
Can use input embedding at time T plus
one and T plus two and so on because all
inputs are available. On the in the
decoder, I'm generating words one at a
time as we saw, right? Each word is
being fed back at the next time. So when
I'm updating this representation, this
word has not gone back in. That next
word is definitely not being generated.
This portion that is
covered by the red box is not available
when I am generating the updated
representation for I N Did that make
sense?
Yes or no?
Right?
I see one yes. Can I get a few more
thumbs ups
to see that this made sense?
Like three, five
seven. That's really bad. Maybe I can
get 10 people to agree with me. Okay,
10. Thank you.
So, this makes sense, right? And so,
this gives us something called masked
self-attention.
When you're training the decoder, you're
going to use exactly the same code as
the encoder
except that at each location you're
going to use a mask which masks out the
future and zeros their weights.
So, for zeros their attention weights.
And then you can use the rest of the
code in much the same way, right? So,
this is masked self-attention.
And you can see why the mask is
required.
Yes, no?
Do you see why the mask is required?
Guys, be a little prompt because I'm
running out of time.
If you don't see it, I can answer
questions. If you see why it's required,
I can move on.
Right, so
>> [gasps]
>> Okay, I can I get like 10 thumbs ups?
So, I think
All right. At least 1/16 of the class
got it. Okay, thank you.
So, this is what we call the masked
self-attention block, right?
The masked self-attention layer
sequentially computes outputs left to
right.
And when you're generating any output,
it masks out the future
in the code because
at least during training because they
not available, right?
And so, this is the masked
self-attention block. It's just the same
as the training encoder side except with
the masking.
And the masked self-attention also
includes an MLP after the masked
self-attention like in the encoder.
So, you can also have multi-head
self-attention exactly the same as in
the encoder. You have many heads.
The only difference being that you still
need the masking.
And so, all of these outputs are
combined and then they're they're the
concatenated outputs are then passed
through an MLP and as someone pointed
out earlier, it's actually the same MLP
applied again and again at each point.
And this MLP tends to be the one that
stores That's right, Edward. This MLP
tends to be the one that stores all the
uh actual knowledge captured by the
model.
You make this smaller,
then your model has less capacity. You
make this larger, the model has more
capacity.
So,
this is your masked multi-head
self-attention block
and the decoder can have many such
blocks.
The decoder, too, is going to have its
own
positional
uh uh embedding to capture relative
position.
So, that leads us to the third poll.
I don't think I'll have time for the
fourth poll, but I'm going to try.
I'm going to give you only 45 seconds
for this, guys,
because we're out of time.
10 seconds.
Okay, I'll stop this right here. Anybody
want to answer this question?
What are the statements that are true?
Just one, right? Self-attention computed
for an N length input requires the
computation of an N cross N attention
matrix because each
uh input pays attention to all
N inputs, and there are N of them.
So, this is the famous transformer
transformer model uh originally proposed
by Vaswani et al. in 2017.
You have uh the one difference from what
I just pointed out is that you actually
have a residual framework uh to make
derivatives flow better. This is
attention is already modeled.
So, the transformer it showed there was
a tremendous decrease in model
computation because recurrent need
recurrent models need sequential
computation. Here, everything could be
done in parallel.
In the original paper, they were
focusing on the computational cost, but
then we found that it's actually it it
does a whole lot more than that.
Then the GPT model, which ChatGPT uses,
is basically just the decoder, which is
actually a conditional language model.
It turns out that you don't need an
encoder. The conditioning can be fed
directly to the decoder, so that was
GPT.
Uh and uh
uh so, you can just put the nature of
your task in the input.
The original paper that it had from GPT
paper showed that just the decoder of
this attention model
uh
beat the state of the art on many
different pretty much every
uh natural language processing task.
The encoder is what is called BERT. BERT
focuses on generating representations
from the input. And it turns out that if
you use this guy, once again, it beats
uh the SOTA on all kinds of tasks. So,
bird was also
uh
bird was also a uh
a landmark in generating
representations. Sriram, every layer on
the decoder is masked.
So, we Here's what we have with
attention is all you need.
Self-attention can effectively replace
recurrence
uh in the sequence-to-sequence models.
It requires positional encoding to
capture positional information. Bruno,
we'll get to that, right? So, can also
be used in regular sequence analysis
settings as a substitute for recurrence,
and currently it's the SOTA in pretty
much all language modeling and AI,
right? And even in computer vision
problems.
So, I'm going to end with a final poll
because, you know what? We love polls.
And I'm giving you only 30 seconds for
this.
Okay, 5 seconds, guys.
All right. Let me end this.
Uh what are the answers?
One and four, right? Bird is the encoder
of the transformer, GPT is the decoder.
And so, that's where we are.
Uh and in the next week, we're going to
have more on transformers and large
language models. On Wednesday,
uh we have Omar Khattab, professor at
MIT, who's going to be doing a lecture
guest lecture on LLMs.
Uh he is Omar is
a brilliant researcher. He's going to be
He's one of
He's already one of the young stars and
he's going to be one of the major stars
of the future, guaranteed.
But what makes Omar special was that uh
it's a matter of great pride to me that
as an undergrad, he was a TA I for IDEA.
And so
uh that makes him kind of always willing
to do a guest lecture for us, although
he's a very busy and very famous man.
And I'd uh
recommend that all of you
please do attend Omar Khayyam's lecture
on Wednesday and inform your friends who
are not in today's lecture as well.
So, did today's lecture make sense to
all of you guys? I'll answer any
remaining questions.
Uh
uh did today's lecture make sense to all
of you guys?
Let me stop the recording.